NYSUT Field Services Department Files. 6174/004
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Ken Low Correspondence (1 of 2), 1973 (Box 69, Folder 12)
  July - October, 1973. Chronological files of memos re strike expenses, payroll requests; memos re Yorktown, Greenburgh, Newburgh, Harrison, and Lay Faculty Association strike settlements; sample ads from Vinton strike, recommended as models; memo re need to communicate to local presidents re Landrum-Griffin Act requirements; list of economic benefits available to NYSUT and AFT members; letters to coordinators expressing thanks for efforts during various strikes; memo from negotiator for school boards to chief school administrators re recent decisions, legislation, with cover memo from Ken Law to regional coordinators noting advice, October 12; Commissioner's decision in fair dismissal case, with cover memo from Ken Law to regional coordinators, October 12; memo from Ken Law to Tom Hobart noting win in Southampton College representation election, October 12; memo re use of vacation time for Jewish holidays, October 11; memos re individual cases of teacher tenure, fair dismissal issues; materials re office procedures re record keeping; Commissioner's decision re Fishers Island re abolishment of a full-time physical education position and creation of two part-time phys ed positions, with cover memo, October 1; telegram from Ken Law requesting $105,000 interest-free loan guarantee from National Education Association for Lay Faculty Association Diocese of Brooklyn strike, September 27; similar telegrams for Newburgh and Harrison strikes; article from American School Board Journal re teacher pay, September; similar article from Reader's Digest, September; memo from the State Education Department re new internal policy re maternity leave, with cover memo from Ken Law to all NYSUT field staff noting possible rationale for locals, September 17; call to local presidents from Tom Hobart for telegrams of support to striking locals; memo to regional coordinators in response to questions re legality of "loyalty oaths" (to support the Constitution) for teachers, September 14
- Ken Low Correspondence (2 of 2), 1973 (Box 69, Folder 13)
- Ken Low Correspondence (1 of 2), 1975 (Box 69, Folder 14)
  March 1 - June 30, 1975. Chronological files re arbitration issues, request for list of locals at impasse; outline for advocate organizing workshop; draft administrative guidelines for Field Services re personnel files; draft contract for Gloversville district, June 17, with cover memo proposing to drop certain items, June 18; NYS Department of Labor Unemployment Insurance Division Guidelines for Payment of Unemployment Benefits between School Terms or During Recess Periods, issued to school district administrators, with cover memo re individual case, June 18; memo re broad implications of Court of Appeals ruling on PERB decision in Jefferson County Improper Practice charge for refusing to bargain in good faith, greatly restricting PERB's ability to impose a remedy, June 17; outline of Plattsburgh Summer Workshop schedule; letter to labor professor at University of Alabama re intent of request for him to speak at Plattsburgh Teachers Institute on benefits of organizing into a single union, June 11; NYSUT Legislative Memorandum in support of Stavisky bill, increasing aid to education, June 5; requests for legal assistance in individual cases (seniority, denial of tenure); report of Tenure Committee re policy recommendations for NYSUT, June 3; operating budget proposed increases; list of reaffiliated and non-affiliated locals, May 30; letter to local presidents urging support for legislation eliminating double penalties for striking, with attached letter from NYS School Boards Association urging opposition, May 29; mailgram from NYSUT president Tom Hobart to United Teachers' Committee of 100 re lobbying effort; budget information re cost of travel per staff member, comparing 1974-75 and 1975-76; list of guest lecturers and topics for Plattsburgh Teachers Institute, May 27; related memos re topics for Plattsburgh Teachers Institute; fact sheet for organizing community colleges in competition with Associated Community College Faculties (ACCF), May 27; 1973-74 Statewide Rankings of school districts for Full Value per Resident Weighted Average Daily Attendance and Full Value Tax Rate per $1000; list of mandatory and non-mandatory subjects for bargaining and related PERB cases, May 28; memo re tenure-related discharge case in Lansingburgh
- Ken Low Correspondence (2 of 2), 1975 (Box 69, Folder 15)
- NYSUT Correspondence (1 of 2), 1974 (Box 70, Folder 1)
  August - November, 1974. Chronological files mostly from Ken Law as Field Services director to regional coordinators; memo to Ken Law from NYSUT counsel Bernard Ashe re copyright laws, November 11; list of affiliated locals, November 1974; list of UNISERV staff and employment dates, 1974-75; NYSUT Service Center addresses and telephone numbers; update on election results for endorsed candidates for state Assembly, Senate, and judicial office, November 11; memo re school nurse teachers, with attached legal opinions, November 5; memo from Ken Law to NYSUT president Tom Hobart re creation of a coordinator position for higher education locals, November 5; list of staff assignments to United University Professions (UUP) chapters, November 1; memo from Robert I. Allen re impasse at Webutuck Teachers Association, October 28; memo from Ken Law re resignation as of January 27, 1975, October 28; memos from Robert I. Allen re strike cost reimbursement for Westbury Teachers Association, Mineola Teachers Association; brief before the U.S. Court of Appeals, Second Circuit, re discharged Westmoreland teacher (Plano), October 21; position (personnel) requests; state Court of Appeals decision ordering reinstatement of teacher (Lezette) in Hudson City school district, October 21; question and answer sheet re staff contract (PSA and CWA) implementation, with cover memo to management staff, October 17; memo to regional coordinators re purchase power program, with attachments, October 11; rules of procedure from Division of Human Rights, with cover memo to regional coordinators, October 2
- NYSUT Correspondence (2 of 2), 1974 (Box 70, Folder 2)
- Ken Low's Books, 1975-1976 (Box 70, Folder 3)
  December, 1975 - August, 1976. Chronological files, mostly from Robert I. Allen, re financial and legal / arbitration issues, including list of American Arbitration Association cases and outcomes; brief for Amsterdam Teachers Association; Commissioner's decisions; Supreme Court decisions; memos re strike expenses; conference and training agendas; position (personnel) requests; memo re unincorporation of NYSUT, January 26, 1976; reimbursement requests; critique from Robert I. Allen to Vito DeLeonardis of Vestal/Elmira Workshop; staff recommendations regarding tenure areas
- Discipline NYSUT Policies/Past Practice/Reprimand Letters, 1979-1982 (Box 70, Folder 4)
  Materials outlining due process and progressive discipline for off-premises conduct, tests for reasonableness; picketing guidelines; use of personal leave or vacation days during inclement weather; memo re arbitrator's decision ruling that NYSUT's policy re outside employment was improperly enunciated and unevenly applied, February 20, 1981; confidential memo to general counsels and coordinators re standardizing NYSUT administrative policies, March 6, 1981; letter from executive director Vito DeLeonardis to Charles Caputo, president of the Professional Staff Association, that NYSUT intended to establish a policy that outside employment had to be cleared ahead of time with NYSUT management in order to determine whether a potential conflict of interest existed, January 6, 1982; letter to Caputo from secretary-treasurer Herb Magidson that unauthorized use of a NYSUT vehicle would be cause for dismissal, February 12, 1982; reply from Caputo, disagreeing with policy, February 16; memo from president Tom Hobart to managers re NYSUT policy partially lifting restrictions on air travel, with attached August 10, 1981, resolution urging NYSUT members to honor Professional Air Traffic Controllers (PATCO) picket lines, January 8, 1982; memo re NYSUT policy re local union elections in compliance with Landrum-Griffin Act, January 21 and February 3, 1982; letter from Vito DeLeonardis to Robert Gordon, president of Lay Faculty Association, informing him that it was not the policy of NYSUT to defend members in criminal cases not involving incidents on picket lines, February 26, 1982; confidential memo to office managers re time off for Holy Thursday, March 10, 1982; letter from Vito DeLeonardis re NYSUT policy re legal representation, March 11, 1982; fact sheet defining past practice; personal and confidential letters of reprimand to Tony Ficcio, coordinator of NYC office, June 23, 1980, and October 23, 1979, and Ron Peretti, December 21, 1981
- NYSUT Community College Conference, 1992 (Box 70, Folder 5)
  Program, "Fighting Back in Scary Times"; registration lists and forms; evaluation forms; correspondence
- Jim Wood Chron May: Dec., 1988 (Box 70, Folder 6)
  May - December, 1988. Chronological files of correspondence of executive director James Wood; replies to job applications; letters from Wood to the bishop of Albany, apologizing for erroneous and inappropriate distribution of resolution re negotiations at St. Catherine's Home, November 23 and December 13; resolution with original handwritten note to Wood, stating that it would be distributed, October 18; materials re New York State Labor-Religion Coalition Conference; agenda for regional staff meeting of December 13; letter from Wood to congressman Sherwood Boehlert's office, listing legislative issues for discussion at meeting, December 1; summaries by Wood of regional directors' reports; correspondence re training programs; analysis of the Brookhaven Hospital campaign, August 9; correspondence re Empire Plan health insurance reimbursement for Hawthorne Cedar Knolls Union Free School District, May-June; correspondence between Wood and member re increasing the number of women among professional ranks of NYSUT, May 13; membership estimates, 1988-89; draft Q&A sheet re new regulations for Excellence In Teaching funds
- James G. Wood Chron Apr.: Dec. (1 of 2), 1988 (Box 70, Folder 7)
  April - December, 1988. Chronological files of correspondence re trouble at United Staff Association at New York University, April 28; confidential memo to president of Communication Workers of America local in Kingston re managerial harassment of CWA members, April 6; list of potential topics for legal column in New York Teacher, April 4; expense reimbursements; requests for office equipment; letters of thanks for help in BOCES organizing campaign; privileged and confidential supplemental report of trial from attorneys to Utica Mutual Insurance Company re O'Neil v. NYSUT, advising appeal, March 15; list of members of Retiree Organizing Committee, March 30; confidential memo recommending upgrade of secretarial position, March 25; memo to NYSUT counsel re NYS Teachers Retirement System credit for World War II veterans who (by virtue of their overseas deployment) had not met the residency requirements to buy back their time, March 24; confidential memo re health of two field representatives at Elmsford Regional Office, request for additional position, March 24; copy of NEA Advocate, February; Newsday clipping, "Schools Fear a 'Tax Revolt,'" March 17; letter from Wood to Vito DeLeonardis re DeLeonardis' retirement, March 2; memo re proposed AFT dues increase, March 2; letter from Wood to president of Baldwin Teachers Association informing him of NYSUT decision not to appeal member's case, March 1; letters to applicants for Regional Staff Director of Southwestern Regional Office, March 1; letters of thanks to field representatives for putting together health and safety training program, February 29; memo from first vice president Antonia Cortese to Executive Committee re policy recommendations from NYSUT's Standing Committee on Occupational Education, with resolution, proposed changes by State Education Department, and related correspondence, February 16; memo from Wood to officers re current organizing efforts, February 18; letter from Wood to Irwin Polishook, president of Professional Staff Congress, requesting assistance in contacting nurse members of PSC, February 11; newsletter by Federation of Nurses and Health Professionals (FNHP), Rx for the Future, winter 1988; draft report for discussion at May 12 Regional Staff Directors (RSD) meeting re format of meetings; letter from Assemblyman Frank Barbaro, chair, Labor Committee, to NYSUT president Tom Hobart re proposed increase in state unemployment insurance benefits, comparative levels in other states, February 3; letter to president of United Liverpool Faculty Association indicating that NYSUT would not represent teacher in 3020a certification revocation proceeding, February 11; letter from John DeGregorio, Suffolk regional staff director, re formation of Suffolk County Task Force on Education and the Economy, February 5; memo re possible dates to begin negotiations for new agreement with Legal Staff Association, February 11; printout listing welfare funds in Elmsford region, by district, with cover memo, February 9; memo re legislation protecting teacher jobs under various circumstances, February 3; letter to bishop of Albany diocese, requesting support from New York State Labor-Religion Coalition for governor's proposed minimum wage and unemployment insurance benefit increases, February 8; sample letter to the editor in support of legislation from bishop and Hobart as co-chairs of coalition, February 1
- James G. Wood Chron Apr.: Dec. (2 of 2), 1988 (Box 70, Folder 8)
  April - December, 1988. Chronological files: memo re Regents' and Commissioner's position on proposed Regional High School of Excellence in technology, February 2; letter from president Hobart to president of United Staff Association re negotiations with New York University, January 29; related memo from Wood to NYS regional director Tony Ficcio, January 29; memos re transfer of director of Southwestern Regional Office to Albany, resulting vacancy, January; memo re special election for Board of Directors vacancy resulting from the resignation of Jim Wood, January 15; letter from Wood to Assemblyman Chesbro with attached list of officers of NYSUT affiliates in Oswego County, January 15; letter to Tom Hobart from attorneys as intervenors in a lawsuit by Rockville Centre School District and Sachem School District against the Empire Plan's premium increase, asking for any information that would assist the case, December 22; letter from Wood to Sen. Sherwood Boehlert's office asking for intervention to assist two retired teachers on waiting list for public housing, facing disqualification under new eligibility rules, January 5; memos to Tom Hobart evaluating recent Wharton management training program, December 18; mentor teacher grant proposal from Syosset school district, October 22, 1987
- Jim Wood Chron (1 of 2), 1989 (Box 70, Folder 9)
  Chronological files: letters confirming intern positions; confidential hearing transcript re letter of reprimand, December 11; agendas for Field & Legal Management meetings; New York State Labor-Religion Coalition meeting notice and Steering Committee resolution, and letter from Wood to Rev. Donald Bauer of Our Lady of Good Counsel Church, noting that his confrontation with the bishop was considered inappropriate, November 27; letter to Rev. Bauer informing him of his selection to receive award from coalition, September 15; arbitration summary in 3020a case in Webster school district, reinstating teacher who had been suspended without pay; memo to Jim Conti re increasing number of cases in which teachers were charged with criminal harassment as a result of use of corporal punishment, need for guidance by NYSUT counsel, November 27; summaries of regional staff directors' reports; memo re meeting on NYSUT's no-smoking policy in anticipation of new state regulations, November 7; letters of thanks to various state elected officials and executive staff for participation in conference by Labor-Religion Coalition, November; letters of invitation to community leaders, inviting them to attend coalition conference, August; letters re medical leaves of absence, promotions; confidential memo re extensive defense of 3020a case in East Rockaway, October 30; confidential memo re training director Ray Ratte's retirement, October 24; confidential memos re salary information re PSA field representatives, October 6; memo re discussion on political endorsement guidelines, September 28; letters from NYSUT president Tom Hobart to presidents of Legal Staff Association (LSA) and Communication Workers of America (CWA) local 1141 re implementation of new smoking restrictions under state law, September 18; memo to regional staff directors outlining topics for discussion re staffing, training, equipment, organizing, upcoming negotiations, September 15; memo re implementation of resolutions by 1989 Representative Assembly; memo re support for striking Teamsters affiliate, a Soft Drink Workers local of drivers for Pepsi-Cola distributors, some of whom made deliveries to schools, September 12; summary of PSA/NYSUT collective bargaining agreement, September 11; requests for reimbursements; arbitration case with PSA over denial of extended sick leave, and confidential cover memo, June 21; denials of education leave; other personnel issues; letter of recommendation from NYSUT president Hobart to Governor Mario Cuomo on behalf of former teacher for appointment to Port of Oswego Authority, June 12
- Jim Wood Chron (2 of 2), 1989 (Box 70, Folder 10)
  Chronological files: letters to managers re excess accumulated vacation days, June 5; letters of rejection to field representative job applicants; denial of education leave request to attend National Women's Studies Association annual conference; denial of extended family sick leave; denial of upgrade request; approvals of release time for PSA officers; agenda for Labor-Religion Conference, focusing on negative effects of NAFTA on U.S. and Mexico workers; request from Jim Wood for three additional field services positions, May 12; request for information from Wood to NYSUT counsel Bernard Ashe re power of Commissioner to recall members of a school board for ignoring directives of Commissioner, and any procedures for voter-initiated recall, May 12; memos re shared decision making data and related issues; confidential memo to regional staff director in Jamestown re plans to bring salary up to its proper level; memo re state aid level for Camden area, May 11; memo re ballot results for president and vice president in Rochester Teachers Association election, May 10; summaries of regional staff directors' reports; requests for reimbursements; summary of satisfaction survey of three NYSUT locals, April 25; draft of substitute resolution re preservation and improvement of fair hearing provisions under section 3020a of Education Law; confidential notices of individual meetings with regional staff directors on topics of staffing, training, equipment, organizing, upcoming negotiations; memo re Rockland-BOCES challenge by NEA, February 27; memo re review of NYSUT crisis reimbursement policies, February 2; memo to NYSUT legal counsel asking for review for potential legal problems of mandatory health questionnaire for new employees, January 31
- James G. Wood Chron (1 of 2), 1991 (Box 70, Folder 11)
  Chronological files: summaries of regional staff directors' reports; Field & Legal Management meeting agendas; confidential PSA grievance hearing report re nonpayment of vision care benefit, September 20; confidential LSA grievance hearing report re non-payment of salary step increase, credit card service fee, vacation buy-back, and professional publications allowance, May 29; confidential CWA grievance hearing report re failure to permit work adjustment through use of flexible hours and inequitable and inconsistent application of other leave provisions, May 16; confidential report of grievance hearing re letter of reprimand, April 12; hearing report for LSA grievance re inequitable and unfair solution of staff attendance at AFL- CIO Lawyers' Conference, April 16; letter to president of Starpoint Teachers Association re reasons for denial of legal representation for member, September 24; related letter from Starpoint T.A. to Tom Hobart, September 9; memo re school district budget and teacher staff cuts at Suffolk, Nassau, Westchester, and Rockland locals, September 20; memos discussing procedures and staffing for legal services; confidential memo re inappropriate hosting of dinners at NYSUT expense, August 19; memo re working with the A. Philip Randolph Institute and Rochester Central Labor Council, August 12; memo to regional staff directors re changes in meal allowance, August 7; memo updating on NYSUT school-restructuring project, July 10; memos and agenda for new local presidents' conference; memos granting PSA and CWA release time; memo re meeting on economic troubles in the Northeast, June 13; memos from Tom Hobart and others re cut in state funding for Teacher Centers, June; memo re NYS early retirement incentive legislation, June 6; confidential memo re questionable expense vouchers, May 20; letter from Political Action Committee to Kick-Out Unproductive Politicians (PACK-UP), with attached no-tax pledge card, and cover memo to regional staff directors noting that the letter had been sent to all voters in Sen. Ralph Marino's home district (Oyster Bay, Nassau County), criticizing Marino for refusing to sign the pledge, December 19; correspondence with Mt. Vernon Federation of Teachers re unsatisfactory presentation by NYSUT counsel Jim Sandner, December; memos re promotions, release time, responses to job applicants, other personnel issues
- James G. Wood Chron (2 of 2), 1991 (Box 70, Folder 12)